我们的下一位演讲者是Nenad Rakocevic
他给我们带来的是"什么是Red"
(掌声)
谢谢Greg. 同时感谢所有
that donated to pay the cost for my trip
为我此次行程进行捐助
so I could make it.
使我能够站在这里给大家做演示的人们。
I've made a lot of Red presentations
我曾经做过很多关于Red的介绍
but newcomers to Red are still coming to me
但是很多初次接触Red的人仍然跑来问我
with this simple question:
这样一个简单的问题：
just "What is Red"
究竟“什么是Red呢？”
because the project has many aspects
因为这个项目涉及的范围非常广泛，
and I can understand that.
这一点我可以理解。
So I'll try in this presentation to give your
所以，我会尽量在这次介绍中给大家
a good view of every part of the project.
做一个全面的展示。
So let's start by an overview of the problem.
那么我们从问题的综述说起。
It's not a picture of my brain cells.
这可不是一张大脑细胞的图片，
It's a computer model of a global map
而是一个目前已知的宇宙的
of the known Universe.
计算机模型图。
That gives you a good picture
这可以让大家对这个问题涉及的范围之广
of the size of the problem (laughter)
有一个直观的印象（笑声）
And actually it's a hint at
这实际上也为
what I was supposed to become
我原本是打算做什么的提供了线索。
because I was studying astrophysics
因为我以前学的是天体物理学
and I switched in college to Computer Science.
后来才转到了计算机科学专业。
My view of the computing world is that
我对于计算机世界的认识是
even today we are still using some primitive
即便是到了今天，我们还在用着一些非常原始的
tools and techniques.
工具和技术。
So we are not very far from these two guys
所以在软件领域我们其实与这两个人
on the software side.
没太多差别。
We are still doing it in a very primitive way
我们仍然在使用一种非常原始的方法做软件开发，
because we keep reinventing the wheels
因为我们不断地重复发明轮子
and constantly are doing the same mistakes
和犯相同的错误，
again and again.
一次又一次。
So AI will be laughing.
相信连机器人见了都会发笑。
At least I hope. :-) (laughter)
至少我希望如此 :-) （笑声）
So if we get back a bit more on the topic
现在回到正题上来
there are actually a lot of programming languages
实际上，世界上已经有相当多的编程语言了
If you look at the Wikipedia list
这是维基百科上的编程语言列表
of programming languages, this is just the A part
以A开头的部分
and that page is not even exhaustive.
甚至就连这部分一页都没能放得下。
So there are literally thousands
所以说编程语言有成千上万
of programming languages.
一点都不夸张。
If you look there you will see some languages
在这里你会发现有一些语言
that were created on the Amiga.
是在Amiga发明的
The famous "Amiga E"
这是著名的"Amiga E"语言，
and AMOS which made by a French guy...
AMOS语言是一个非常聪明的法国人发明的，
a very bright guy, whose name is François Lionet.
他就是François Lionet。
This Basic was featuring a DSL.
AMOS BASIC可以看做是一种领域特定语言（DSL）
It was a tool I used to have
我曾在20多年前
more than 20 years ago.
使用过它。
The DSL was meant for animations...
这种领域编程语言(DSL)的用途是制作电影动画...
...it was compiled to native code.
...它可以编译成本地代码。
And the whole interpreter and compiler and IDE
AMOS整套的解释器、编译器和集成开发环境
for AMOS was fully written in assembler.
都是用汇编语言编写的。
So this guy was quite an inspiration for me.
这位仁兄给了我相当大的启发。
Despite so many programming languages
尽管已经有了这么多的编程语言
and tools we are still searching for a newer,
和工具，但我们还是在不断寻找更新、
better solution.
更好的方法。
The problems we are facing every day
软件领域经常遇到的问题
in the software world are quite known now
都已经是老生常谈了。
but we keep hitting them.
但是我们仍然在不断地与之相遇。
Like exploding complexity... bloatware...
比如日益增加的软件复杂度...软件膨胀...
No I don't mean Java, of course. (laughter)
当然我说的不是Java(笑声)
Not thinking about Java. :-P
不要联想到Java :-P
Slow performance... Black boxes, which can be
再比如运行效率差...以及黑盒子，
closed source software, for example.
这一点可以以闭源软件为代表，
Which is often a big problem when trying
当你遇到的bug超出了你所能掌控的范围时，
to solve bugs that you can't reach.
这通常会是一个大问题。
So instead of spending our time hitting these walls
所以与其花费时间在这些问题上碰壁，
we should have fun doing programming
不如把编程变成一件快乐的事情。
because programming is about having fun.
因为编程本来就应该是充满乐趣的一件事情。
And this is the spirit we should have when
这是我们在使用计算机进行工作时
we are facing our computer and working on it.
应该有的精神状态。
It's like in those times where programming
就像在那些编程*仅仅*代表一种乐趣
was *only* fun.
的年代一样。
Since then, since the 80's
从那时起，即上个世纪八十年代，
a lot of revolutions happened.
发生了很多技术变革。
And currently we have two -- I think --
现今，我认为在计算机技术领域
very important changes in the computing world.
有两个非常重要的变化
The first one is augmenting the power
第一个是计算机的计算能力增强的途径
of computers by adding new cores
由提升CPU的频率
instead of raising the frequency of the CPUs.
开始转变为增加CPU核数。
This has deep implications for programming tools.
这个变化会对编程工具产生深远影响。
The other main revolution is that we are all now
另一个重要的变化是，市场的重心正在逐渐
switching to mobile devices.
向移动端转移。
The market is changing very fast.
市场在飞速发展，
So the programming tools also need to adapt.
编程工具也应该顺应潮流而变。
Despite those changes,
然而尽管发生了这些变革，
we are still using very old tools, in fact.
实际情况是，我们仍然在使用一些非常古老的工具。
So I took just the five most popular
我仅就五个最流行的语言来说一说这个问题
programming languages from the Tiobe index...
这些语言摘自著名的
...the famous index.
Tiobe编程语言排行榜。
Yeah, C is still the main one
是的，C语言仍然是最重要的一门语言，
and it's been around for almost 40 years now.
迄今为止它已经被广泛使用了将近40年。
That's quite a long time in computing!
在计算机世界里，这可是一段相当长的时间！
And C is absolutely not meant to address
很显然C语言绝对不是为了解决
the modern needs for computing.
现代的计算需求而被发明出来的。
And if you look at the other ones
如果你再看看其他语言
that's almost more or less the same thing.
也都大同小异。
Fortunately for us, some people...
所幸的是，有这么一些人...
...some very rare people were aware of this
...一些非凡之士意识到了这个问题，
and capable of giving an answer to these issues.
并且给出了问题的答案。
People like Carl (gestures to Carl Sassenrath)
比如Carl（向Carl示意）
who invented Rebol... fantastic tool.
他发明了Rebol...这门了不起的编程语言，
Probably one of the greatest inventions
可以说是过去20年中编程领域
in the programming world in the last 20 years.
最伟大的发明之一。
So Rebol was a good solution, or a very
在很多领域，Rebol都表现不错，
good solution for a lot of concerns.
或者说非常棒。
*But not all.*
*但是，并不是全部领域*
Something I would like to show to Carl...
我想向Carl展示一些东西...
...maybe he hasn't seen it?
...或许他还没有见过？
The wonders Rebol was doing, until recently,
直到最近，Rebol取得的最好成就，
was just the Rebol community praising it
只是Rebol社区的人们在称赞它
and trying to explain to people how Rebol
并努力向他人解释Rebol是一门多么
was a productive tool, and expressive.
高效，表达能力多么强的编程语言。
But recently a scientific study tried to measure
近期有一项科学研究试图衡量
the expressiveness of programming languages.
各门语言的表达能力。
So they did it. And Rebol... *surprise*! Is number 3.
这是他们的研究结果。令人吃惊的是，Rebol居然排名第3。
In fact: number 1 and number 2 are DSLs.
实际情况是，排名第一和第二位的是两门领域特定语言（DSL）
So guess who's the first one? (laughter)
猜猜是谁排名第一？（笑声）
So that just confirms something we all knew
其实这不过是验证了我们
since the beginning.
早就知道的事情：
Rebol is a very productive tool
Rebol是一门生产效率极高的语言，
and that's now proven. (laughter)
只不过现在有了明证。（笑声）
But Red tries to go beyond what Rebol provides.
但是Red想要做的是超越Rebol。
Mainly in terms of implementation
主要是在实现方式方面
not in terms of language semantics or syntax.
而不是语法或语义方面。
But more in terms of toolchain, implementations,
更多的是在工具链、实现方式
and spreading.
和延伸方面。
So what is Red, really?
那么究竟什么是Red呢？
Red is what I call
Red是一门我称之为
a *Full-Stack Programming Language*
*全栈式编程语言*的语言。
Maybe you've heard about full-stack developers?
或许大家都听说过全栈工程师吧？
So this one is a full-stack programming language.
现在又来了一门全栈式编程语言。
And probably it's main characteristic
从某种意义上说它的主要特色是
is that it's a true general purpose
这是一门真正意义上的
programming solution.
通用编程语言。
There are many languages
有相当多的编程语言
that *advertise* as general purpose...
将自己*标榜*为通用编程语言...
...but they are not as broad as Red can be.
...但是它们触及的范围都没有Red语言来的广泛。
The other great characteristic about Red
Red语言的另一个特色是
is that it's a stand-alone toolchain
它只有一个独立的工具链
so we are not depending on the standard
这样的话我们就可以不依赖
classic C toolchain, we have our own one.
经典的C语言工具链这样的标配了，我们有自己的工具链。
Another important aspect of Red
Red的再一个重要方面是
is it's about *freedom*.
它是*自由*的。
Since the beginning my motivation for Red
由于我开发Red语言的初始动机是
was to get free of any kind of restrictions
突破各种限制
or any kind of limits.
或者限度，
I want users of Red to feel the same.
我希望使用Red的人们也有相同的感受。
So Red is simple to use, *thanks to Rebol*...
Red的简单易用*受益于Rebol*...
...but Red has no arbitrary restrictions.
...但是Red不存在任何局限性。
We try to address every possible need
我们着眼于方方面面的需求
and every possible aspect so it
这样它就可以
can be deployed, ported to any platform we need.
被部署、移植到任何我们想要的平台。
Also, something very important in programming:
另外，在编程中非常重要的一点：
you need to be feeling in control of your tool.
对自己所使用的工具要有掌控感。
Often you use some tools that can be powerful
你会经常用到一些非常强大
but you don't control them, because
但是不能自由掌控的工具，因为
you don't understand what's happening inside.
你不了解它的内部是怎么运行的。
Often because they are black boxes.
当然也通常因为它们是黑盒子。
Or because they are sitting on a big pile of layers
或者是它们位于软件的一大堆层级当中
of software so you can't just understand
以至于你不能了解
what is happening inside.
内部究竟是怎么运行的。
And an important last thing :-)
还有最后一点，非常重要的一点 :-)
is the *Fun*. Yeah, we want the fun back.
就是*快乐*。是的，我们想要找回编程的快乐。
Some people that tried to use Red
一些用过Red
or Red/System, after compiling and running
或者Red/System的朋友在成功编译和运行
their first program successfully
他们的第一个程序之后
came back to me and said:
跑来告诉我说：
"It's great because, it's fun."
“非常好玩，棒极了！”
"I just tried it, and it worked, and it was great."
“我只是试了一下，居然运行起来了，太棒了。”
People get that feeling -- what I was talking about
人们找到了那种我之前所说的
That feeling from the 80's.
来自于上个世纪80年代的感觉，
Where you feel really in control
那种你真的可以对你的编程工具
of your programming tool.
完全掌控的感觉。
So I'll try to explain what I mean by
接下来我会说一说我所说的
"Full-Stack Programming Language" and
“全栈式编程语言”与
"True General-Purpose Programming Language".
“真正意义上的通用编程语言”是什么。
So I made this chart:
我画了这张图：
"Domain Scope of Application"
部分主流编程语言的
for a few of the main programming languages.
“领域适用范围图”。
For example, assembler is drivers
例如，汇编语言用来编写驱动程序，
and very low-level code.
属于非常低级的代码。
You can see that Java is really limited in its
可以看到Java的能力局限于
ability to address different abstraction levels.
解决各种抽象层的问题。
Ruby is quite wide;
Ruby的适用范围很广;
maybe it doesn't go down to the OS?
但还没有低到操作系统层级吧？
I don't know if the Ruby interface
我不知道通过Ruby接口来
for calling OS API is really good or not.
调用操作系统API是好还是坏。
Rebol has quite a wide scope.
Rebol的适用范围相当广泛。
Rascal is a very specific programming language.
Rascal是一种非常特别的编程语言，
It's a kind of DSL,
它实际上是一种领域特定语言（DSL），
which is meant for writing other DSLs.
用来编写别的领域特定语言（DSL）。
So it's standing at the meta-DSL level.
因此它的适用范围在meta-DSL层。
So where is Red on that scale?
那么Red的适用范围呢？
Well Red is aiming at addresing all needs
Red的目标是满足所有这些需求，
from the bottom to the top.
从底层到顶层，
Because I don't want to have to rely on another tool.
因为我不想依赖另外一种工具。
I want the Red programming language
我想让Red语言
to be able to address all the needs
不依赖别的任何东西
without relying on something else.
就能满足所有这些需求。
So you will tell me that it's quite impossible
有人会说
to make a language that addresses
发明一门适用范围如此之广的语言
such a wide scope.
是不可能的。
And you'll be right.
他很可能是对的。
But Red has a trump card.
但是Red不一样，它有自己的王牌。
Red/System covers the low layers
Red/System语言会负责较低的层级，
and Red covers the upper layers.
Red语言则负责较高的层级。
They are integrated together
二者可以相互协作，
and working together.
配合无间。
So Red/System, in fact, is a dialect of Red.
Red/System实际上是Red的一种方言。
You can use it separately
既可以单独使用，
or directly embedded totally in Red.
也可以直接嵌入在Red代码中使用。
So let's have a look at the platforms we support.
下面再看一看所支持的系统平台。
First on the desktop,
首先是桌面系统，
we support the classic 3 main players.
我们支持三大主流操作系统。
We also support some additional
同时也支持其他一些操作系统
operating systems like Syllable.
比如Syllable。
We would like to support FreeBSD
我们希望能够支持FreeBSD,
but we had some low-level issues
但是由于遇到了一些底层的问题
and no FreeBSD experts among us
同时缺少FreeBSD专家
to solve those, so for now it's a bit stalled.
来解决这些问题，因此目前暂时被搁置了。
But we could probably get Red ported
但如果可能的话，我们会尽快将Red移植到
on FreeBSD rapidly.
FreeBSD上。
Then we also want to address
我们也要支持
the embedded market, starting with Android.
嵌入式平台市场，是从Android开始着手的，
which we already support.
目前已经可以支持Android了。
The next one will be iOS.
下一个将会是iOS。
And we already run on Raspberry Pi
Red目前已经可以运行在
which is becoming quite popular.
日渐流行的Raspberry Pi了。
I guess Bo will do some demonstrations
我猜Bo可能会在明天给大家
maybe tomorrow.
做一些演示。
We also have an experimental port on Arduino
我们还有一个Arduino上的实验性质的移植版本
We started with AVR 8-bit.
是为8位的AVR做的。
But it's an experiment for now
当然目前只是实验性质的，
because other boards are coming
因为不久其他一些电路板上的版本就会出现，
like 32-bit boards or Raspberry Pi.
像是32位的或者Raspberry Pi，
So 8-bit support may not be the thing to do now.
所以8位的并不是当务之急。
We also want to support virtual machines.
我们还会支持虚拟机。
We want to be able to connect to .NET
我们想要连通.NET平台
to the JVM, and to JavaScript.
JVM平台以及Javascript平台。
There are basically two methods
实现这一点
to achieve this.
一般有两种方法。
We can have a bridge, keeping Red like it is now
一种方法是使用桥接器，保持Red原样不动
and bridging with these virtual machines.
使用桥接的方式来访问这些虚拟机。
Or we can develop a new backend
另一种方法是为Red和Red/System
for Red and Red/System
开发新的后端
to be able to compile directly to the bytecode
使之能够直接编译成这些虚拟机的
of these virtual machines.
字节码。
So we have those two options.
所以这样我们有两种选择。
We started by making some bridges for the JVM.
我们是从为JVM创建桥接器开始着手的。
We'll try to choose each time
我们会为不同的虚拟机选择
the right solution -- the best one for the job.
最适合的方案。
So right now we are bridging with the JVM.
所以现在是采用桥接的方式连接JVM虚拟机。
But we will probably compile for JavaScript directly.
但对于JavaScript可能会采用直接编译的方式。
We have asm.js now, so we have
现在我们已经有了asm.js，这样我们就有了
a really interesting platform to support.
一个相当吸引人的平台来支持。
I expect Red and Red/System
我相信Red和Red/System能够
to run quite fast on that.
在这上面运行很快。
More practically, just another view of how it works
Red工作机制中更加务实的一面是，
So you have Red: one binary.
只需要一个可执行文件，
You download and get all these features.
将其下载下来，所有的特性就都具备了。
You can run a Red script directly from memory.
你可以直接从内存中执行Red脚本，
You can compile it to an executable.
可以把它编译成一个可执行文件。
You can cross-compile it...
还可以进行交叉编译...
we'll get back to that feature.
稍后我们再详细说这个特性。
You can also directly compile Red/System scripts,
你也可以直接编译Red/System脚本，
if you don't want to use the Red layer
如果你不想使用Red
but you want to code a low-level application.
而是想编写一个底层应用程序的话。
And you can also now compile shared libraries
你还可以编译共享库
that opens the door for spreading Red
这样就为Red的延伸打开了方便之门，
by plugging it everywhere we can.
即可以将它以插件的形式安装到任何我们想要安装的地方。
You can also launch Red in a console mode
你还可以启动Red的控制台模式
so we have a Red console.
这样我们就拥有了一个Red控制台。
So cross-compilation... Red is now able to cross-compile
关于交叉编译...其实现阶段就可以进行交叉编译，
to other systems, from any system to another.
从任一系统编译其他任何一个系统所需要的文件。
In fact it's able to compile from any platform
实际上它可以从任一运行着Rebol的平台
where Rebol runs to any other platform.
编译出其他任何平台的可执行文件。
To achieve that you don't need a HOWTO
做到这一点不需要一份HOWTO文档
You don't need a tutorial.
也不需要一份教程
You don't need to search on the Net for
更不需要去网络上进行搜索
how to achieve it.
该怎么实现。
You simply pass a "-t" command and the target ID
你只需要添加一个“-t”命令和相应的目标ID就可以了，
and that is all.
就这些。
A target ID is just an entry in a configuration file
目标ID只是配置文件中的一个条目，
a simple Red dialect, where we just list
这个配置文件是一种Red的方言，在其中我们只是列出了
some options for the target platform.
目标平台的一些可选项。
So currently we have this list of about 8 targets
到目前为止，我们共支持8个目标平台
So we can cross-compile from any one
这样我们可以在任一平台上交叉编译其他平台需要的文件，
to any other, as long as Rebol
只要源平台上
runs on the source platform.
运行着Rebol。
So as you can see we are supporting mainly
可以看到我们目前主要支持
x86 and ARM based platforms.
基于X86和ARM的平台。
To get a bit deeper inside the toolchain
更深入看一看会发现我们的工具链
we have several parts.
分为几个部分。
We have the classical couple: compiler, linker.
有编译器和链接器这对经典组合。
So the compiler layer is able to mainly address
编译器主要支持
those two backends, x86 and ARM.
x86和ARM这两种后端。
But we plan to extend it to support ARMv7
但是我们打算对其进行扩展以支持ARMv7
"thumb mode" and 64-bit platforms.
的Thumb模式和64位的平台。
We also will add the virtual machine backends.
我们以后还会支持虚拟机后端，
So JavaScript, JVM bytecode... Dex for Dalvik
例如Javascript、JVM字节码，Dex指的是Dalvik虚拟机的dex档案，
as an alternative for JVM on Android platform.
是Android平台上的JVM，
And MSIL stands for the bytecode name
MSIL指的是.NET平台上的
for the .NET platform.
MSIL中间语言代码。
So the Linker is supporting the main file formats.
这样的话链接器就可以支持所有主流的文件格式了。
We will extend it to also support static libraries.
我们后面将会对它进行扩展使其能够支持静态链接库。
So you'll be able to compile a Red program
那时你就可以把Red程序编译成
as a static library so you can link it later
静态链接库，之后与其他外部工具链——
with another external toolchain, like a C one.
比如使用C语言编译的——进行链接。
That's an alternative way to spread Red
这是另外一条延伸Red语言的途径，
and to enable people to use Red
允许它
in third-party toolchain languages/applications.
和第三方语言或应用程序构成的工具链一起使用。
And we also go down to the kernel level
我们甚至深入到了内核层级
and we will provide support for building
这样就可以直接使用Red语言
kernel drivers, or even full operating systems
开发内核驱动程序，
directly from Red.
甚至是完整的操作系统。
And currently we have experimental
到目前为止已经可以支持Windows内核驱动程序的开发，
Windows kernel driver support, already working.
虽然是实验性的，但是是可以使用的。
If there are kernel driver developers here
如果在座的各位中有谁从事驱动程序开发
you can have fun with it. :-P
可以享用一下。 :-P
Last one: something that doesn't exist
最后一点，据我所知，
as far as I know, in the classic C toolchain:
有一样东西在经典的C语言工具链中是没有的：
we'll have a packager layer
我们将提供一个打包工具，
which is not implemented yet, but will be soon.
这个目前还没有实现，但是很快就会有。
We'll start with the Android APK backend.
我们最先从Android的APK后端做起。
So the point of this layer
这个工具主要用来
is just to take several files and package them
将一些文件打包
and format them like the target platform expects.
生成目标平台所需要的格式文件。
So we'll support Android, we'll support iOS.
我们会支持Android,也会支持iOS，
But such a packager could also be used
其实这样一个打包器也可以用来
for packaging web applications.
打包web应用。
So like Java does for the .WAR format
就像Java中的.WAR包一样
which has very interesting abilities
WAR包有提供了很多吸引人的功能，
like simplifying the deployment of web applications
比如简化应用的部署过程，
and being able to version them
进行版本管理，
or roll back deployment
或者对部署进行回滚，
which are great things to have.
这些都是相当有用的。
Another aspect of the toolchain
关于工具链的另外一点说明是
is that currently the toolchain
它目前处于自举阶段，
is bootstrapped in Rebol 2.
代码是用Rebol 2开发的，
We are already running on that for two years.
迄今为止已经这么做有两年了。
But the final Red will have a JIT compiler.
不过最终形态的Red将会拥有一个JIT编译器，
To have a JIT compiler we need to go self-hosted.
而实现JIT编译器需要实现自托管。
So we need to have Red written in Red.
因此我们需要使用Red语言自身来重写Red。
That's the only way to get a proper JIT compiler.
这是开发一个适合的JIT编译器的唯一途径。
So we'll most probably work on that next year.
我们很可能会在下一年就做这些工作。
I have a few slides about the Red language itself.
我做了很多介绍Red语言自身特性的幻灯片
But I won't go into too many details
但是今天不会涉及太多细节的东西，
because it will take too much time.
因为这需要很多时间。
The first thing to understand about Red language
理解Red语言的第一个要点是
is that it's very close to Rebol.
它非常接近Rebol语言。
You have some of the main Rebol characteristics
它具有Rebol的主要的特征，
like definitional scoping and dynamic binding.
比如definitional scoping和动态绑定。
You also have the ability to program in Red
你在使用Red进行开发时可以
using whatever paradigm you want.
选择你想使用的任何范式。
So *"paradigm-neutral"* is an expression
我非常喜欢Gabriele (Santilli)所说的
from Gabriele (Santilli) and I like it very much
“范式中立”这一表述，
because it expresses really well this ability
它准确描述了
to not be bound by a specific paradigm.
不局限于任何一种范式的能力。
A difference between Red and Rebol
Red和Rebol之间的一个区别是
is that in Red you can optionally type local variables
在Red中你可以选择性地指定函数中局部变量的类型，
and you can also type the return value
同时还可以指定
of functions.
返回值的类型。
So in Rebol, it doesn't have much meaning
在Rebol中，这样做意义不大，
because it's an interpreter, and it has no value.
因为它只是是个解释器，这样做没有必要。
But for a compiler, it has great value.
但是对于编译器就不一样了，是非常有必要的。
Because annotating those types in the function
因为在函数中指定这些数据的类型
allows the compiler to generate
可以使编译器产生
much more specialized, faster, and efficient code
比没有指定时更加明确、快速和
than without the annotations.
高效率的代码。
Red is "optionally typed". So you can type it or not.
在Red中数据类型是可以选择性地指定的。指定或者不指定都可以，
It depends on your needs, or the way you program.
完全取决于你的需求或者编程的方式。
So you can do it in the Rebol way
你可以选择类似于Rebol的方式编程，
which will be very flexible.
这种方式非常灵活，
But you will end up with slower performance.
缺点是性能较差。
Or you can do it the static way
你也可以选择静态的方式，
where you type everything
即为所有的一切都指定好类型，
and the compiler will be able to do more type-checking
这样的话，编译器就会做更多的类型检查工作，
so you will get some warnings or some errors
你就可以在编译阶段而不是运行阶段
at compile-time instead of getting them at run-time.
获得警告或者错误提示。
Also, if you are not using the type annotations
另外，如果你没有添加类型描述，
the compiler will be able in some cases
在某些情况下，编译器可以
to do some type inference.
做一定的类型推断工作，
So it will be able to guess the types for you.
帮助你推测变量的类型。
But as Red, like Rebol, is a very dynamic language
但是和Rebol一样，Red也是一门动态性很高的语言，
the extent to which the inference engine
所以推测引擎的功能
can guess those types is quite limited.
是非常有限的，
So, it will be a little help, but not a big one.
因此它能够提供的帮助也是很有限的。
We of course have Unicode support.
我们当然会支持Unicode。
Red source code is UTF-8.
Red源代码的编码格式是UTF-8。
We'll provide some external codecs for other encodings.
我们也会为其他编码格式提供一些外部的编解码器。
Internally, basically, Red stores and manages
基本上，Red语言内部存储和操作
Unicode strings like Python does
Unicode字符串的方式
in the latest versions.
与最新版本的Python语言相似。
So the internal storage is fixed size.
内部存储是定长的，
But it can take from 1 byte to up to 4 bytes
但是每个不同的码点可能会占用
per codepoint.
1到4个不等的字节。
And the system will automatically adapt
系统会根据输入
and adjust the size according to the input
和对字符串所做的修改
and the modifications you are making on the string.
自动适应和调整所需要的长度。
Another part that's very important in Red
Red的另外一个重要方面
is the concurrency support.
是对并发的支持。
But currently it's not implemented
但是由于目前尚未实现
so I won't go in details about that.
所以我就不进行深入探讨了。
We want to support two main things:
两项主要的事情：
we want to support task parallelism
一是任务并行，
so you can execute several threads of code
这样就可以在多核上
in parallel using other multiple cores.
并行执行多个线程的代码。
We'll probably use the Actor abstractions.
我们可能会采用Actor模型。
But there are other abstractions
但是从Red项目开始以来
that since the beginning of the Red project
我们考虑过众多其他的并发模型。
are getting a lot of traction. Like Go routines,
比如Go routines，
which are becoming a big selling point
这是Go语言的一个
for the Go language.
相当大的卖点。
So that's something we should consider
也许我们也应该为Red考虑一下，
also for Red, maybe...
或许是...
in addition or as a replacement for actors
作为actor及其他模型的补充，
and other kinds of abstractions.
或许是将它们替代。
So when we get to the point of implementing
因此当我们要着手实现
the concurrency support we need to revise
并发支持的时候会重新考虑
all the design choices and see
所有相关的设计决策，
if we can update them by copying
看一看是否可以
some other successful strategies.
复制其他的成功策略来完善它们。
We also want to have some level of
我们还想通过使用单指令流多数据流（SIMD）
data parallelism using either SIMD
或是多核处理技术来实现
or multicore processing.
一定程度的数据并行。
So basically that will be using the ability
主要会用到
to parallelize processing of Red series.
Red系列值并行处理的功能。
We would also like to address something
我们还打算解决一些
that Rebol currently doesn't really address
目前Rebol尚未能真正解决的问题，
which is: how do you make a dialect?
这就是：怎么实现一种方言，
Or how do you make a DSL?
或是领域特定语言（DSL）？
Rebol is great for that --
Rebol非常擅长于此
it's probably one of the best tools for doing that
它可能是做这类事情的最好的工具之一
because it has PARSE and because
因为它拥有PARSE以及
it has some interesting qualities
其他一些令人惊艳的特征，
that make it a good choice for that.
这些使得它成为一个不错的选择。
Anyway building a DSL or building a dialect
然而创造一门领域特定语言或者方言
is not something easy.
可不是一件那么容易的事情。
Because you need to design it first.
因为你首先需要进行设计，
That's already a lot of work.
这里面就有相当多的工作要做。
And then you need to implement it.
然后你还要去将其实现。
And implementing a DSL or a dialect
实现一种领域特定语言或者方言
is implementing an interpreter or a compiler.
其实就是实现一个解释器或者编译器。
For that you are almost left alone with the code.
到了这一步，你唯一拥有的就只是代码了。
So you don't have really a framework
你并没有一个真正意义上的框架
for doing that.
来辅助你做这些事情。
And it's possible to leverage the qualities
一种可行的方案是
of the Rebol language in Red
借助Rebol语言的力量
or maybe even in Rebol
在Red或者Rebol中
to make a kind of meta-DSL
创造一种用来设计DSL的DSL（meta-DSL），
that will allow you to be much more productive
借助它可以使你的工作更加富有成效，
and give you a framework
同时也提供了一个
for building new dialects and new DSLs.
创建新的方言和领域特定语言（DSL）的框架。
Basically it will be something like
总的说来它可以看做一个
a higher-level version of PARSE.
更高级的PARSE。
You can think about it, for example,
举个例子，可以这样设想它，
like having PARSE with an event loop
在使用PARSE解析一个事件轮询时，
and the event loop will be hidden.
这个事件轮询会被隐藏起来，
Something like Visual Basic does.
就像Visual Basic做的那样。
And you will just implement events
你只需要实现事件
to create your DSL as an interpreter or compiler.
就可以创造你的领域特定语言了，不论是以解释器还是编译器的形式。
So what does the Red compiler do?
Red的编译器用来做什么事情呢？
The Red compiler converts Red code
它会把Red代码转换为
into Red/System which is the lower-level layer.
低层级的Red/System代码。
I just wanted to show you what it looks like.
下面我会给大家演示一下。
So if we take a very simple Red expression
首先我们有一个非常简单的Red表达式，
the Red compiler parses it
然后Red编译器会对其进行剖析，
and uses a stack abstraction to place the arguments
并且使用一个堆栈（stack）结构来存放参数。
In fact it uses two stacks: one for calls
实际上这里用到了两个堆栈：一个调用栈，
and one for arguments.
一个数据栈。
And then the emitter will produce Red/System code
之后代码生成器就会基于此
based on that.
生成Red/System代码。
So what you see on the right side
右边的部分就是
is the Red/System output for that expression
那个表达式最终生成的Red/System代码，
calling the Red runtime API.
称之为Red运行时API。
Another singular aspect of the Red compiler
我认为Red编译器和Red语言
and the Red language
另外一个非凡的方面是
is that it combines several kinds of approaches
它把几种相当独特的方法
which is something quite unique, I think.
结合在一起。
So basically you have a static compiler.
最基本的是一个静态编译器。
That static compiler will generate code
这个静态编译器会与一个内存的解释器
with an interpreter inside, and tomorrow
一起生成编译后的代码，将来
a JIT-compiler embedded inside your executable.
还会在可执行文件中内嵌一个JIT编译器。
All these three parts will be able to work together
以上三部分会
in a very collaborative way.
协同工作。
So for example, the compiled code
比如，编译后的代码
can call the internal interpreter
可以调用内部的解释器
which itself can call back into the compiled code.
而解释器本身也可以反过来调用编译后的代码。
Same thing for the JIT compiler.
JIT编译器也是一样。
It's a bit abstract, but I can show you at the end
听起来有点抽象，但是在演示稿
of the presentation a slide
的最后一张
with a practical case for such an approach.
会有一个采用这种方法的实例。
In fact, such an approach is a very powerful tool
其实，这是一种解决非常复杂的语义问题
to solve very complex semantic cases.
的非常强大的方法。
For example, compiling symbolic code,
例如，编译符号代码
which is something quite difficult to achieve.
是一件非常困难的事情。
But if you combine different approaches
但是如果结合不同的方法
you can find a very efficient solution.
就会找到一个非常有效的方案。
So this is just a very simple example
我用一个非常简单的示例
of how Red code looks.
来演示一下Red代码长得什么样。
You have the same principle like in Rebol
与Rebol一样，
so you have a marker which is [Red]
最开始是一个由[Red]标识符及
followed by a block that constitutes a header
后面紧跟着的文件头方块组成的标记，
and your code goes after that.
之后是你的代码。
Hello world is just [print "Hello World"]
Hello world只需要写[print "Hello World"]就可以了。
like in Rebol, and the rest of the code
就像在Rebol中一样。其余的代码
probably looks very much like Rebol
也看起来非常像Rebol代码，
except maybe for the [return: [type!]]
有一点例外，就是[return: [type!]]，
which is optional, but it's the kind of
这个是可选的，它属于我前面讲过的
optional typing I was talking about just before.
可选的类型指定特征。
So you have an example there.
现在你看到示例了。
It's not mandatory to put it, but if you put it
这个并不是强制要求的，但是如果这么做了的话
the compiler will generate better, faster code.
编译器就会生成更好更快的代码。
So just a bit more detailed view
以上就是对Red语言的内部细节
of the internals of Red, and the different parts
和不同的组成部分的介绍，
so you get a better picture of how
你现在应该对它们的关联关系
all those elements are related.
有了更清晰的认识。
So if we start from the guy on the right
让我们从最右边的人说起。
we have a command-line front-end script
这里有一个命令行脚本
which is written currently in Rebol2
目前是用Rebol2写的，
and behind it we have the two stacks
在它后面是两个堆栈，
for the two compilers. One for Red, which is
分别属于两个编译器。一个是Red的，
shorter because it just emits code for Red/System.
它比较简短，因为产生的是Red/System代码。
And one for Red/System
另一个是Red/System的，
which goes down to the packager
从上到下直到打包器，
so it can emit and produce binary files.
它可以生成二进制文件。
All that is the toolchain written in Rebol 2.
上面所说的是使用Rebol2写的工具链。
On the left side, you have the Red runtime.
左边的是Red的运行时，
Which is quite a big piece of code,
它的代码量很大，
actually probably bigger than the other side.
甚至比整个右边的都大。
And which is written in Red/System.
这是用Red/System写的。
So you'll find all the real power on that side
“大腕”们都位于这一边。
for example, all the datatypes,
例如，所有的数据类型，
all the natives, the mezzanine code,
全部本地代码（natives），中间层代码，
the interpreter, the bridges -- like the Java one
解释器，桥接器——像刚才提到的Java桥接器，
which is already available.
目前已经为大家提供了。
The memory manager and the low-level interfaces
内存管理器和用来访问底层部件
to the underlying pieces.
的低层级接口。
So for example you have the direct access
例如你不仅可以直接访问
to the OS API but also to the kernel.
操作系统的API，而且还可以访问内核代码。
On Linux you can do syscalls directly.
在Linux系统上可以直接进行系统调用。
And if necessary you can go even down
如果需要的话，甚至可以深入到硬件层级，
to the hardware and call very low-level features.
来调用非常低级的功能。
Maybe I just missed the Red Console also
我可能忘了介绍Red的控制台
which is also written in Red
它也是用Red语言写的，
and Red/System for the low-level parts.
Red/System负责比较低级的部分
About Red/System... I have a small presentation
说到Red/System...明天我还会有一个比较小的
tomorrow specifically on Red/System, because
专门介绍Red/System的演示，因为
it's kind of a new thing in Red compared to Rebol.
对比Rebol来说，这是Red中的一个新玩意。
So I have just a slide about Red/System
所以我只准备了一张幻灯片来介绍Red/System，
to give you just an overview.
大家有一个大概的印象就好了。
So basically it's just a kind of C-level language
事实上，它是一种与C语言同一级别的语言
but with a Red syntax.
却使用的是Red语言形式的语法。
So it often feels like coding in Red
所以感觉像是在用Red语言编程
but with very low-level datatypes and actions.
但是使用的是非常低级的数据类型和操作。
So it's statically compiled.
它采用的是静态编译的方法。
It's currently not optimized at all. :-)
到目前为止还没有进行任何优化。:-)
But it's only 4x slower than optimized C
不过它只比经过“-O2”级别优化编译的C语言代码
compiled with "-O2".
慢4倍。
So it's quite good, actually it's very good.
因此它还是相当不错的，实际上是非常不错。
Because once we add the optimization layers
因为一旦我们对其进行了优化，
we'll be very, very close to C.
运行效率将会非常非常接近C语言。
We probably won't beat it, but that's not the goal.
虽然不会超越C语言，那不是我们的目标，
But we'll be very, very close.
但是会非常非常接近。
So Red&#x2F;System will be a really viable alternative to C.
这样的话Red/System将会是C语言的一个非常可行的替代语言。
And it already does wonders in some
例如，它已经在图像处理领域
image processing for example
取得了不错的成绩。
that Bo (Lechnowsky) will show you tomorrow.
Bo (Lechnowsky)会在明天给大家做一个这方面的演示。
Something that the C language doesn't have
下面是C语言本身不具备，
or most very low-level languages don't have:
或者说大多数低级编程语言也都不具备的东西。
Red/System has namespaces,
Red/System有命名空间的概念，
which are something like contexts in Rebol
类似于Rebol里的语境
but very static, so we are using the CONTEXT keyword
但是是静态的，所以我们在Red/System中也用CONTEXT
to declare them in Red&#x2F;System also.
来声明。
And you can also use the WITH keyword
你还可以使用WITH关键字
to put some part of your code inside a context
将部分代码置于某个语境中，
something like declarations in other languages.
类似于其他编程语言中命名空间的声明。
We have a very limited type system in Red/System
在Red/System中数据类型非常有限，
We have nine types.
共有9种类型，
So basically the same datatypes as C.
基本上与C语言一致。
The function datatype isn't a fully first-class datatype
函数类型并不算是"一等公民"，
I have hesitated a lot about that, because...
我曾对此犹豫再三，因为...
if I make it a fully first-class datatype
如果我将它实现为一个完整意义上的“一等公民”类型的话，
People will start asking for me
可能就会有人要求我
to make Red/System a functional language.
将Red/System设计成一种函数式编程语言。
Which is possible but it's not the goal.
这一点是可以做到的，但是它并不是我们的目标。
It doesn't serve any purpose, so I'm quite reluctant
这样做其实没有什么用途，因此我很不愿意
to add new features on that datatype.
去给这个数据类型添加新功能。
We have type inference,
我们还有类型推断，
so you don't have to specify the data type
不用指定局部变量的数据类型，
for local variables, the compiler will guess it.
编译器会进行推测。
We also have a limited type-casting
兼容的数据类型之间可以进行简单的类型转换，
between compatible data types.
当然也是一个非常有限的功能。
And we have something C doesn't have
我们还有C语言不具备但
but C++ has, which is some level of reflection.
C++具备某种程度的反射机制。
So you can declare some function in Red/System
你可以在Red/System中声明一个
with a variable number of arguments
参数个数不确定的函数。
you can put brackets around them
可以使用方括号将参数们括起来
and inside the body of that function
然后在函数内部
you can walk through that list of arguments
遍历参数列表，
and you can query the type of each argument.
查询每个参数的类型。
So that's quite a powerful feature,
这是一个相当强大的特征，
and actually Kaj de Vos used it to build
事实上Kaj de Vos已经利用这个功能用Red/System构建了
a VID-like dialect in Red/System
一个与VID类似的方言
which is quite a feat because
这是一项伟大的壮举，因为
we don't have symbols in Red/System :-)
在Red/System语言中并不能进行符号式编程。:-)
So it looks like VID but it's using that feature
这个方言看起来很像VID，但是运行方式采用的是
to run it, and it's really great.
反射机制，真的非常棒。
We also have a preprocessor in Red/System
在Red/System中还有一个预处理器，
but I would like to drop it in the next major release
但是我打算在下一个较大版本发布中将其去除，
because we have more problems with that
因为它给我们带来的麻烦要远大于
than we have advantages.
给我们带来的好处。
So we'll keep a few of them
我们会有选择地保留一部分
but we need to rethink it and redesign it.
但是需要重新规划和设计。
The #define is a very powerful option
#define是一个相当强大的工具，
because it gives you almost the same power
因为它带给你的是与C语言中的宏几乎一样的能力，
as C macros, so you can even use parameters.
你甚至可以向它传递参数。
We also want to have some low-level CPU support
我们还设想要一些能够访问CPU的低层级的功能，
currently we have access to some CPU registers
目前可以跨平台
in a cross-platform way.
访问一些CPU的暂存器。
We have access to the stack --
我们可以访问堆栈（stack）——
you can manipulate the native stack
你可以在Red/System层级跨平台
at the Red/System level in a cross-platform way.
对本地堆栈进行操作。
And we'll add support for interruption I/Os
我们还会添加对I/O中断
and other very basic CPU features.
以及其他CPU基本功能的支持。
Maybe we'll add some inline assembler support
可能还会增加一些对内联汇编的支持
but it's not currently a big need.
但是目前还不是一个要紧的需求。
A few metrics about the Red project.
下面是对Red项目的一些说明。
So it's BSD, for most of the codebase.
大部分代码采用的是BSD协议
And the runtime parts of Red are "BSL"
Red的运行时采用的是“BSL”协议
which is the "Boost Software License"
它的意思是“Boost软件协议”（Boost Software License）
which is even more liberal than BSD.
这个协议比BSD协议还要宽松，
So you have even less restriction than BSD.
限制更少。
We are on GitHub since the beginning
我们从一开始就将代码托管在了Github上，
we have 9 committers... I think that's wrong
我们有9个核心提交者...我想这里有点小差错
it's 11 committers now.
现在应该是11个了。
We have more than 2,000 commits
共计2000多次提交
without counting merge commits.
不包括提交合并。
We have about 500 tickets in the bug tracker
在bug追踪库里有大约500个tickets
but they are almost all closed
大多都已经处于关闭状态了。
we try to get them closed as fast as possible
我们尽可能做到bug一出现就其将解决掉
to avoid piling them up.
以防它们积累起来。
Because once they pile up,
因为一但积累起来，
you almost never get them processed.
就几乎不可能对它们进行处理了。
So we really need to keep that very, very low.
所以非常有必要将它们的数量保持在一个极低的水平。
We have a lot of unit tests
我们还有非常多的单元测试用例
which are built by Peter Wood
这些都是Peter Wood写的
who has done great work on that.
他为此做了相当大的贡献
It's very, very helpful.
帮了我们的大忙。
And here you have a few metrics
下面是关于
about the size of the source code
源代码代码量的统计，
for the Red and Red/System parts.
分别是Red的和Red/System的，
For the compiler, for the linker.
从编译器和链接器两方面考量。
So you can see for yourself
你可以亲眼看到
that's a really small codebase.
这个代码库有多么小。
So you can achieve a lot, thanks to Rebol :-)
多亏有了Rebol，一个人可以取得相当大的成就。
you can achieve a lot with a small codebase
使用一个很小的代码库、聊聊数行代码
and a few lines of code.
就可以取得这么大的成绩。
You can compare that to other toolchains
与其他工具相比较，
and you'll often see one or two
（代码量上）通常会看到一到两个
orders of magnitude of difference.
数量级的差距。
Of course they are probably covering
固然它们的问题覆盖面
more ground than we do.
比我们的要广。
But with such a small codebase
然而我们仅仅使用一个很小的代码库就
we are already covering a lot of ground.
涵盖了相当大的范围。
So we still have a lot of work
我们仍然有很多工作要做，
It's still under heavy construction.
项目仍然处在繁忙的开发中。
So we have some big core parts missing, still.
我们还有几个核心部分尚未开发。
We need object support, which is not yet there.
我们需要支持对象，这部分还没有。
We don't have proper error handling yet
也还没有合适的错误处理机制，
because we need OBJECT! for that.
我们需要OBJECT!类型（即对象）来支持它。
We lack type checking for arguments
在编译器的某些部分
in some parts of the compiler.
还缺乏对参数类型的检查功能。
We don't have the I/O yet, but...
目前我们还不支持I/O，不过
of course objects and I/O are very high on the list
对象和I/O的优先级很高
They probably will be implemented this summer.
大概会在今年夏天开发出来。
We want some level of concurrency support
在1.0版本中我们打算支持一定的并发功能，
in the 1.0, and we naturally also want
自然我们还打算有
a modular compilation and module system.
一个模块化编译系统和一个模块体系。
We will probably provide a very minimal Red IDE
我们可能会提供一个非常小的Red IDE，
which will probably just be a code editor
它可以用作一个编辑器
plus a debugger... and we will work
外加调试器...我们会在以后的版本中
to extend that in future versions.
对它进行扩展。
We also want full documentation
我们要有一份全面的文档，
so that's a big showstopper to release a 1.0
这会是1.0版本发布过程中出彩的一幕。
so we have a lot of work to write that documentation
编写文档和教程
and to write tutorials.
有相当多的工作要做。
And of course, we need to have a new website
当然了，为了准备1.0版本的发布
for the version 1.0 launch.
我们还需要准备一个新的网站。
But that's not all... :-)
但是这还不是全部... :-)
that's not the real Red.
这还不是真正的Red。
The real Red will be the 2.0.
真正地Red将会出现在2.0版本中。
And we have a pretty good cast for that (laughter)
我们有一个相当华丽的阵容（笑声）
So what is "The Real Red"?
那么什么才是“真正的Red”呢？
In fact, what I've presented so far
实际上，到目前为止我所说的
is a kind of scaffolding.
只是一堆建筑材料。
Because the real Red is this one.
因为真正的Red将会是这样的，
The real Red will be basically a JIT compiler
真正地Red基本上就是一个JIT编译器
that will be able to work as a static compiler too.
它也可以用作静态编译器。
The whole internal architecture
整个的内部结构
will be totally different than the current one
将会与目前这个处于自举阶段的版本
implemented in the bootstrapped version.
大不相同。
So it will be plugin-oriented
它是面向插件的，
so basically the compiler and the toolchain
所以编译器和工具链基本上
will be an empty shell -- a framework --
就是一个外壳——或者说一个框架——
where you will be able to plug in some modules
从语法分析到目标文件的生成各个阶段，
to add features at every stage of the compilation.
你都可以为之添加模块
From the parsing to the generation of the files.
来增加新的功能。
You will have an API to work with.
你都会有与之对应的API来做这些事情。
So I will provide the framework
这样我提供的是一个框架
and the minimal modules to make it work
和最少数量的模块，
to have the same level of features as the 1.0.
它们能够提供与1.0版本的相同的功能点。
And such an API will be of course documented
这些API当然会写入文档中，
so anyone will be able to modify
这样的话人人都可以以一种互不影响
and add new features to the compiler
和非常结构化的方式
in a very isolated way, and very structured way.
对编译器做修改和添加新功能。
Such an API could also be called at runtime.
这些API也可以在运行过程中被调用
So I can let you imagine the options and possibilities
所以大家可以想象一下
with modifying the compiler itself and the toolchain
在运行时修改编译器本身和所使用的工具链
at runtime.
将会带来多少可能性。
So it's possible at runtime
在运行过程中修改语言本身
to change the language itself or add new features.
或是添加新的功能是完全可行的。
It may sound totally crazy
这些听起来相当疯狂
but it's something other languages
但是这正是某些正在成长中的语言
which are growing right now
在做的事情，
are doing... for example, the Scala language
比如，
is doing exactly that.
Scala就是这么做的。
And some people from the Scala community
一些来自于Scala社区的人
are using this kind of feature to do wonders in Scala
利用这些功能做出了令人惊叹的东西。
For example, one very smart guy
举个例子，一个非常聪明的哥们
used this API to add parallel support to for loops
使用这个API为循环添加了并行计算支持，
by using the GPGPU for parallelizing that
实现并行计算使用的是GPGPU，
using OpenCL as a low-level layer.
底层使用的是开放计算语言（OpenCL）。
So that's a very powerful feature
所以说这是一个非常强大的特性，
and also it makes the compiler architecture
同时也使得编译器的架构更加健壮，
much more solid and allows people to contribute
也使得人们
in a much easier way
以更加简单
and a much more structured way.
更加架构化的方式贡献代码。
So the implication is that the current codebase
这里的言外之意是当前这个编译器的代码库
of the compiler... so in the Red internal diagram
...位于Red内部结构示意图
it was the right side of the blocks...
的右侧的部分...
The current codebase in Rebol 2
目前这个使用Rebol 2写的代码库
is kind of disposable code.
用完就可以丢弃。
So since the beginning, I wrote it very fast
从一开始我就写得非常快，
thinking that I will dump it quickly
觉得可以在一年之内就可以
in about a year,
堆砌起来，
and be able to recode it in Red rapidly.
之后就可以用Red自身快速地重写一遍。
But we changed a lot of things in the project
但是由于中间我们修改了很多东西，
we adjusted to the evolving environment
为应对环境的变化做了很多调整
so we are not yet there.
因此现在尚未达到预期的目标。
So we will first go 1.0 in the bootstrapped version
所以我们在1.0版本中先发布这个自举的版本
and the 2.0 will be the self-hosted version
而后在2.0版本中再发布使用Red重写后的
with the toolchain recoded in Red.
自托管的版本。
The whole Red runtime part will stay the same
整个Red运行时部分将会保持不变，
because it's coded in Red/System
因为它是用Red/System写的，
so it will survive, and that's a very big codebase.
它会被保留下来，这是一个非常大的代码库。
So the only part that will be recoded
这样的话只有使用Rebol 2写的部分
will be the Rebol 2 codebase, which are
需要被重写，基本上
basically the Red and Red/System compilers.
就是Red和Red/System的编译器部分。
Just a few words about the project organization:
简单介绍一些这个项目的管理结构：
we have two collaborators on GitHub
在GitHub上有两位合作者，
which means there's one admin and two other people
这样就有一个管理员和两个拥有管理员权限的
who have admin rights. So if I get hit by a bus
其他成员。如果我不幸被车撞了，
these two guys could take over the source code
这两名成员就会接管Red代码库中的源代码
in the Red repository and manage it.
并对其进行管理。
We have about 11 contributors to the codebase
从开始到现在我们共有11名贡献者。
since the beginning. We have a mailing list.
我们有一个邮件列表，
We have a Facebook page, an IRC channel
一个Facebook页面，一个IRC频道，
with a nice IRC bot from Andreas
里面有一个出自Andreas之手的非常可爱IRC机器人
for reporting commits.
用来报告代码的提交情况。
And of course we are seeking other people
当然我们也在努力寻找
who are interested in contributing
有兴趣贡献代码
and participating in every way
以及以任何一种方式参与到这个项目中来的同路人
because it's quite a big project...
因为这是一个极其宏大的项目...
and we need a lot of helping hands.
我们需要很多援手。
Last but not least :-)
最后一点，也是非常重要的一点 :-)
I've invested in this project... since I've started
从两年半之前开始，
about 2 years and a half ago...
我已经把我的每一分积蓄
every last cent of savings I had. :-)
都投入到了这个项目当中。 :-)
So I'm really believing totally in the project
因此我对这个项目的成功
and the success of the project.
有着十足的信心。
But I run out of money quite quickly. :-)
但是，很快我就经济拮据了。
Since a year ago, I'm living only on donations
一年以来，我完全依靠
that users and followers are sending to me.
这门语言的使用者和追随者的捐助生活。
So I want to thank them a lot
所以在此我对他们表示诚挚的谢意
because I wouldn't be here without them
因为没有他们我不会走到今天，
and Red wouldn't be at this stage
如果没有人们的支援的话
or probably wouldn't be existing
Red也不会走到现今这个阶段，
if people weren't supporting me.
甚至可能根本就不会存在。
So thanks a lot, and we need to continue
所以真的非常感谢！我们需要继续
to support it to make it a reality.
对它进行支援，使它早日完成。
Thank you all for listening.
谢谢大家！
(applause)
（掌声）